<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter id="shards-architecture" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Architecture</title>
    <section id="shards-architecture-overview" revision="1">
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>
            Hibernate Shards is an extension to Hibernate Core that is designed to encapsulate and minimize the
            complexity of working with sharded (horizontally partitioned) data. Hibernate Shards can be conceptually
            divided into two areas, both of which you will need to understand in order to be successful. The two areas
            are:
            <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
                <listitem>
                    <para>Generalized sharding logic</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Application specific sharding logic</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            We'll discuss each of these areas in turn.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="shards-architecture-general" revision="1">
        <title>Generalized Sharding Logic</title>
        <para>The primary goal of Hibernate Shards is to enable application developers to query and transact against
            sharded datasets using the standard Hibernate Core API. This allows existing applications that use Hibernate
            but do not yet need sharding to adopt our solution without major refactoring if and when they do reach this
            stage. This also allows application developers who are familiar with Hibernate, need sharding, and are starting from
            scratch to become productive in a short amount of time because there will be no need to ramp-up on a new
            toolset. With this goal in mind, it should come as no surprise that Hibernate Shards primarily consists of
            shard-aware implementations of many of the Hibernate Core interfaces you already know and love.
        </para>
        <para>
            Most Hibernate-related application code primarily interacts with four interfaces provided by Hibernate
            Core:
            <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <classname>org.hibernate.Session</classname>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <classname>org.hibernate.SessionFactory</classname>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <classname>org.hibernate.Criteria</classname>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <classname>org.hibernate.Query</classname>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            Hibernate Shards provides shard-aware extensions of these four interfaces so that your code does not need to
            know that it is interacting with a sharded dataset (unless of course you have specific reasons for exposing
            this fact). The shard-aware extensions are:
            <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <classname>org.hibernate.shards.session.ShardedSession</classname>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <classname>org.hibernate.shards.ShardedSessionFactory</classname>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <classname>org.hibernate.shards.criteria.ShardedCriteria</classname>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <classname>org.hibernate.shards.query.ShardedQuery</classname>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            The implementations we provide for these four shard-aware interfaces serve as a sharding engine that knows how to apply your
            application-specific sharding logic across your various data stores. We don't expect application developers
            to need to write much code that knowingly interacts with these interfaces, so if you do find yourself
            declaring or passing around Sharded instances take a step back and see if you can make do with the parent
            interface instead.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="shards-architecture-application" revision="1">
        <title>Application Specific Sharding Logic</title>
        <para>
            Every application that uses Hibernate Shards will have its own rules for how data gets distributed across
            its shards. Rather than attempt to anticipate all these rules (an effort practically guaranteed to fail) we
            have instead provided a set of interfaces behind which you can encode your application's data distribution
            logic. These interfaces are:
            <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <classname>org.hibernate.shards.strategy.selection.ShardSelectionStrategy</classname>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <classname>org.hibernate.shards.strategy.resolution.ShardResolutionStrategy</classname>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <classname>org.hibernate.shards.strategy.access.ShardAccessStrategy</classname>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            The implementations you provide for these three interfaces plus the id generation implementation you choose
            (more on this in the Sharding Strategy chapter) comprise the
            <emphasis>Sharding Strategy</emphasis>
            for your application. The sharding engine described in the previous section knows how to use the Sharding
            Strategy you provide.
        </para>
        <para>In order to help you get up and running quickly, Hibernate Shards comes with a couple simple
            implementations of these interfaces. We expect that they will aid you in your prototyping or in the early
            stages of actual application development, but we also expect that, sooner or later, most applications will
            provide their own implementations.
        </para>
        <para>For more information on Sharding Strategies please consult the chapter of the same name.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="shards-architecture-requirements" revision="1">
        <title>System Requirements</title>
        <para>
          Hibernate Shards has the same system requirements as Hibernate Core, with the additional restriction
          that we require Java 1.5 or higher.
        </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
