<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="shards-limitations">
    <title>Limitations</title>
    <section id="shards-limitations-api" revision="1">
        <title>Incomplete Implementation of Hibernate API</title>
        <para>
            In order to speed-up the initial release of Hibernate Shards, some
            parts of the Hibernate API that we rarely use were left unimplemented. Of course things that
            we rarely used are probably critical for some applications, so if we've left you out in the cold
            we apologize. We're committed to getting the rest of the API implemented quickly. For details on which
            methods were not implemented, please see the Javadoc for <classname>ShardedSessionImpl</classname>,
            <classname>ShardedCriteriaImpl</classname>, and <classname>ShardedQueryImpl</classname>.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="shards-limitations-cross-shard" revision="2">
        <title>Cross-Shard Object Graphs</title>
        <para>
            Hibernate Shards does not currently support cross-shard object graphs.
        </para>
        <para>
            In other words, it is illegal to create an association between objects A and B when A and B
            live on different shards. The workaround is to define a property on A which uniquely identifies an
            object of type B, and to use that property to load object B (remember what life was like
            before Hibernate? Yeah, just like that.)
        </para>
        <para>
            For example:
            <programlisting>
                --need domain for examples--
            </programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
            In some applications your model may be constructed in such a way that it is difficult to make this kind
            of mistake, but in some applications it may be easier. The scary thing here is that if you make this
            mistake, Hibernate will consider the "bad" object in the list to be a new object and, assuming you have
            cascades enabled for this relationship, it will create a new version of this object on a different shard.
            This is trouble. In order to help prevent this sort of thing from happening we have an interceptor
            called <classname>CrossShardRelationshipDetectingInterceptor</classname> that checks for cross-shard
            relationships on every object that is created or saved.
        </para>
        <para>
            Unfortunately there is a cost associated with using the <classname>CrossShardRelationshipDetectingInterceptor</classname>.
            In order to determine the shard on which an associated object resides we need to fetch the object from the
            database, so if you have lazy-loaded associations the interceptor will resolve those associations as part
            of its checks.  This is potentially quite expensive, and may not be suitable for a production system.
            With this in mind, we've made it easy to configure whether or not this check is performed via the
            "hibernate.shard.enable_cross_shard_relationship_checks" property we referenced in the chapter
            on configuration.  If this property is set to "true" a <classname>CrossShardRelationshipDetectingInterceptor</classname>
            will be registered with every <classname>ShardedSession</classname> that is established.  Don't worry,
            you can still register your own interceptor as well.  Our expectation is that most applications will have
            this check enabled in their dev and qa environments and disabled in their staging, load and performance,
            and production environments.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="shards-limitations-txns" revision="1">
        <title>Distributed Transactions</title>
        <para>
            Hibernate Shards does not provide support for distributed transactions within
            a non-managed environment.  If your application requires
            distributed transactions you need to plug in a transaction management implementation that supports
            distributed transactions.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="shards-limitations-interceptors" revision="1">
        <title>Stateful Interceptors</title>
        <para>
            We've done our best to make sure that, by and large, Hibernate Core code runs just fine when using Hibernate
            Shards. There are, unfortunately, exceptions, and one of those exceptions is when your application needs
            to use an
            <classname>org.hibernate.Interceptor</classname>
            that maintains state.
        </para>
        <para>
            Stateful interceptors need special handling because, under the hood, we're instantiating one
            <classname>org.hibernate.SessionImpl</classname> per shard. If we want an
            <classname>Interceptor</classname> associated with the
            <classname>Session</classname>, we need to pass in whatever
            <classname>Interceptor</classname> was provided when the
            <classname>ShardedSession</classname> was created. If that
            <classname>Interceptor</classname> is stateful, the
            <classname>Interceptor</classname> state for one
            <classname>Session</classname> will be visible in all
            <classname>Sessions</classname>. When you consider the sorts of things that are typically done in stateful
            <classname>Interceptors</classname> (auditing for example), you can see how this can pose a problem.
        </para>
        <para>
            Our solution is to require users to provide a
            <classname>StatefulInterceptorFactory</classname> when they establish their
            <classname>Session</classname> objects (which are really
            <classname>ShardedSessions</classname>).  If the provided
            <classname>Interceptor</classname> implements this interface, Hibernate Shards will ensure that a
            fresh instance of the type of <classname>Interceptor</classname>
            returned by <classname>StatefulInterceptorFactory.newInstance()</classname>
            will be passed to each <classname>Session</classname>
            that is established under the hood.  Here's an example:
            <programlisting><![CDATA[
public class MyStatefulInterceptorFactory extends BaseStatefulInterceptorFactory {
    public Interceptor newInstance() {
        return new MyInterceptor();
    }
}
]]></programlisting>

        </para>
        <para>
            Many <classname>Interceptor</classname> implementations require a reference to the
            <classname>Session</classname> with which they're associated. In the case of a stateful
            <classname>Interceptor</classname>, you want your <classname>Interceptor</classname>
            to have a reference to the real (shard-specific) <classname>Session</classname>, not the shard-aware
            <classname>Session</classname>. In order to facilitate this, you have the choice of having the type of
            <classname>Interceptor</classname> that is constructed by the
            <classname>StatefulInterceptorFactory</classname> implement the
            <classname>RequiresSession</classname> interface. If the
            <classname>Interceptor</classname> constructed by the
            <classname>StatefulInterceptorFactory</classname> implements this interface, Hibernate Shards will provide the
            <classname>Interceptor</classname> with a reference to the real (shard-specific)
            <classname>Session</classname> once the factory constructs it. This way your
            <classname>Interceptor</classname> can safely and accurately interact with a specific shard.  Here's an example:
            <programlisting><![CDATA[
public class MyStatefulInterceptor implements Interceptor, RequiresSession {
    private Session session;

    public void setSession(Session session) {
        this.session = session;
    }

    ... // Interceptor interface impl
}
]]></programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
            Due to the basic nature of the problem we don't expect this to change anytime soon.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="shards-limitations-replicated-data" revision="1">
        <title>Replicated Data</title>
        <para>
            Even though this is a framework for horizontal partitioning, there is almost always
            read-only (or at least slow changing) data that lives on every shard. If you're just
            reading these entities we don't have a problem, but if you want to associate these
            entities with sharded entities we run into trouble. Suppose you have a Country table
            on every shard with the exact same data, and suppose WeatherReport has a Country member.
            How do we guarantee that the Country you associate with that WeatherReport is associated
            with the same shard as the WeatherReport? If we get it wrong we'll end up with a cross-shard
            relationship, and that's bad.
        </para>
        <para>We have a number
            of ideas about how to make this easy to deal with but we have not yet implemented any of them.
            In the short term, we think your best bet is to either not create object relationships between
            sharded entities and replicated entities. In other words, just model the relationship like
            you would if you weren't using an OR Mapping tool. We know this is clunky and annoying.
            We'll take care of it soon.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
