<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="shards-resharding">
    <title>Resharding</title>
    <para>
        When an application's dataset grows beyond the capacity of the databases
        originally allocated to the application it becomes necessary to add more databases, and
        it is often desirable to redistribute the data across the shards (either to achieve
        proper load balancing or to satisfy application invariants) - this is
        called
        resharding. Resharding is a complicated problem, and it has the potential to cause major
        complications in the management of your production application if it is not considered during the design.
        In order to ease some of the pain associated with resharding, Hibernate
        Shards provides support for virtual shards.
    </para>
    <section id="shards-resharding-virtual" revision="1">
        <title>Virtual Shards</title>
        <para>
            In the general case, each object lives on a shard. Resharding consists
            of two tasks: moving the object to another shard, and changing
            object-shard mappings. The object-shard mapping is captured either by the shard ID
            encoded into the object ID or by the internal logic of the shard
            resolution strategy which the object uses. In the former case, resharding would require
            changing all the object IDs and FKs. In the latter case, resharding could
            require anything from changing the runtime configuration of a given
            <classname>ShardResolutionStrategy</classname>
            to changing the algorithm of the
            <classname>ShardResolutionStrategy</classname>. Unfortunately, the problem of changing object-shard
            mappings becomes even worse once we consider the fact that Hibernate Shards does not support cross-shard
            relationships. This limitation prevents us from moving a subset of an object graph from one shard to
            another.
        </para>
        <para>
            The task of changing object-shard mappings can be simplified by adding a level
            of indirection - each object lives on a virtual shard, and each virtual shard is mapped to
            one physical shard. During design, developers must decide on the maximum number of physical shards
            the application will ever require.  This maximum is then used as the number of virtual shards, and these
            virtual shards are then mapped to the physical shards currently required by the application.
            Since Hibernate
            Shards'
            <classname>ShardSelectionStrategy</classname>,
            <classname>ShardResolutionStrategy</classname>, and
            <classname>ShardEncodingIdentifierGenerator</classname>
            all operate on virtual shards, the
            objects will correctly be distributed across virtual shards. During resharding,
            object-shard mappings can now simply be changed by changing virtual shard to physical shard
            mappings.
        </para>
        <para>
            If you're worried about correctly estimating the maximum number of physical shards your application
            will ever require, aim high.  Virtual shards are cheap.  Down the road you'll be much better off with extra
            virtual than if you have to add virtual shards.
        </para>
        <para>
            In order to enable virtual sharding you need to create your <classname>ShardedConfiguration</classname>
            with a Map from virtual shard ids to physical shard ids.  Here's an example where we have 4 virtual
            shards mapped to 2 physical shards.
<programlisting><![CDATA[
Map<Integer, Integer> virtualShardMap = new HashMap<Integer, Integer>();
virtualShardMap.put(0, 0);
virtualShardMap.put(1, 0);
virtualShardMap.put(2, 1);
virtualShardMap.put(3, 1);
ShardedConfiguration shardedConfig =
    new ShardedConfiguration(
        prototypeConfiguration,
        configurations,
        strategyFactory,
        virtualShardMap);
return shardedConfig.buildShardedSessionFactory();
]]></programlisting>
            In order to change the
            virtual shard to physical shard mapping later on it is only necessary to change the
            <classname>virtualShardToShardMap</classname> passed to this constructor.
        </para>
        <para>
            We mentioned that the second task during resharding is moving data from one
            physical shard to another. Hibernate Shards does not try to provide
            automatic support for this as this is usually very application-specific, and
            complexity varies based on the potential need for hot-resharding, deployment
            architecture of the application, etc.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
